Exercises
Create a new repository on GitHub to hold your assignments for the Databases module. Create a new branch for Checkpoint 1. Submit your answers.

What data types do each of these values represent?

"A Clockwork Orange"
42
09/02/1945
98.7
$15.99
Explain when a database would be used. Explain when a text file would be used.

Describe one difference between SQL and other programming languages.

In your own words, explain how the pieces of a database system fit together at a high level.

Explain the meaning of table, row, column, and value.

List three data types that can be used in a table.

Given this payments table, provide an English description of the following queries and include their results:

     SELECT date, amount
     FROM payments;

     SELECT amount
     FROM payments
     WHERE amount > 500;

     SELECT *
     FROM payments
     WHERE payee = 'Mega Foods';
Given this users table, write SQL queries using the following criteria and include the output:

The email and sign-up date for the user named DeAndre Data.
The user ID for the user with email 'aleesia.algorithm@uw.edu'.
All the columns for the user ID equal to 4.