EXERCISES

1. Write out a generic SELECT statement.

SELECT <column1, column2, ... column7> or *
FROM <table1>
WHERE <condition>


2. Create a fun way to remember the order of operations in a SELECT statement, such as a mnemonic.

I'm not sure if you want this list since it was the one mentioned in the checkpoint: 

SELECT
FROM
WHERE

Or whether you want this more extensive list even though it wasn't discussed in the checkpoint (I found it online):

SELECT
FROM
WHERE
GROUP BY
HAVING
ORDER BY

I'll assume until corrected that you want the former list. 

Here's my mnemonic: 

SFW or Superman Flies Wherever


3. Given this dogs table, write queries to select the following pieces of data:

Intake teams typically guess the breed of shelter dogs, so the breed column may have multiple words (for example, "Labrador Collie mix").

- Display the name, gender, and age of all dogs that are part Labrador.

SELECT name, gender, age
FROM dogs
WHERE breed LIKE '%Labrador%';

- Display the ids of all dogs that are under 1 year old.

SELECT id
FROM dogs
WHERE id < 1;

- Display the name and age of all dogs that are female and over 35lbs.

SELECT name, age
FROM dogs
WHERE gender='female'
AND weight > 35;

- Display all of the information about all dogs that are not Shepherd mixes.

SELECT *
FROM dogs
WHERE breed NOT LIKE '%shepherd%';

- Display the id, age, weight, and breed of all dogs that are either over 60lbs or Great Danes.

SELECT id, age, weight, breed
FROM dogs
WHERE weight > 60
OR breed='great dane'; 


4. Given this cats table, what records are returned from these queries?

SELECT name, adoption_date FROM cats;

All the names and adoption dates of all cats. (If any values in 'adoption_dates' are NULL, the result will be NULL too.) 

SELECT name, age FROM cats;

All the names and ages of all cats.


5. From the cats table, write queries to select the following pieces of data.

Display all the information about all of the available cats.

SELECT *
FROM cats;

Display the name and sex of all cats who are 7 years old.

SELECT name, sex
FROM cats
WHERE age=7;

Find all of the names of the cats, so you don’t choose duplicate names for new cats.

SELECT name
FROM cats
WHERE intake_date <= '2016-01-12';


6. List each comparison operator and explain when you would use it. Include a real world example for each.

>
Greater than, used when comparing 2 values
Example: Comparing height in inches.  60 > 59 

<
Less than, used when comparing 2 values
Example: Comparing distance in km.  80 < 100

=
Equal to, used when comparing 2 values
Example: Comparing two car prices. 15,000 = 15,000

<=
Less than or equal to, used when comparing 2 values
Example:  When deciding whether someone can buy a ticket for a rated R movie without being accompanied by parent/guardian. If the person is less than or equal to 16 yrs old, the person can't buy a ticket without a parent/guardian.  Age <= 16. 

>=
Greater than or equal to, used when comparing 2 values
Example: When deciding on whether to let someone ride a rollercoaster. If the person is equal to a certain height or taller, he/she can ride the rollercoaster.  Height >= 48 inches

!=
Not equal to, used when comparing 2 values
Example: Comparing two temperatures. 38 != 45 

<>
Greater than or less than, used when comparing 2 values. This is equivalent to !=. 
Example: See != operator example above. 

LIKE
Used to pattern match a string, example: "input LIKE 'cat'"
Example: Searching a list of first names that match 'Tom'. Anyone with the first name 'Tom' will be a match, but no other names will match. 

BETWEEN
Implemented like "a BETWEEN x AND y", this is equivalent to "a >= x AND a <= y"
Example: When trying to narrow down an age range of people to invite to a singles party. Anyone who is greater than or equal to 30 yrs old but (and) also less than or equal to 50 yrs old. 

IS DISTINCT FROM
Used as "expression IS DISTINCT FROM expression", this should be used in place of <> when one of the inputs could be null.
Example: You want to find all names in a list where the value is not unknown. 

IS TRUE / IS FALSE
Used in the format "expression IS TRUE" when the input could be null. Always returns either true or false.
Example: You want to know if a statement on an exam is true or false. 

IS NULL
Determines if the contents of a cell are null. Can be used in conjunction with "NOT"
Example: You want to determine whether someone's age is missing on a medical form. 

AND
Requires both expressions to be true for the row to be returned.
Example: In order for someone to become a member of a fraternity, the person must be both male and at least 18 yrs old. 

OR
Requires one of the expressions to be true for the row to be returned
Example: In order to qualify for a job, a person must have either a bachelor's degree or four yrs of work experience. 

NOT
Requires the expression to be false for the row to be returned
Example: In order for a person to join a sorority the person must not be male. 


7. From the cats table, what data is returned from these queries?

SELECT name FROM cats WHERE gender = ‘F’;

All the names of cats where the corresponding gender is 'F'. 

SELECT name FROM cats WHERE age <> 3;

All the names of cats where the corresponding age is not equal to 3. 

SELECT ID FROM cats WHERE name != ‘Mushi’ AND gender = ‘M’;

All the IDs of cats, where the corresponding name is not equal to 'Mushi' or 'M'. 